we're already dropping in yeah like if
you look at the two-year-old you got the
no
then you got this notion of like this
set of words
results in changes in behavior
sure and then this set of words results
in changes of behavior
that i can predict then this set of
words results in changes behavior that i
can predict and control
now i'm full-fledged adult
there's no like there's no pretense
she's like she just iterates through
combinations of words until she finds
the one that pushes the button she's
looking to push
like okay cool thank you for not like
not deceiving me
into thinking that right other than they
are
right right well then you'll watch at
four
what will happen and she'll start
playing around with lying
right right theory of mine drops in
right and then this whole idea of well
wait a minute i can
i can make reality happen
i distinctly remember coming in my
four-year-old daughter you know we told
her don't eat the cookies and you came
in and they're all over her face you
know it's like so where'd the cookies go
i don't know
did you eat cookies no what are they
cooking you know
but what about that uh chocolate on your
face
oh okay you know now all of a sudden
it's like ah
now i can't just mold reality completely
to my world
so uh yeah the way in which kids lie and
the more they lie that's actually a
better sign overall because it shows
cognitive flexibility and creativity as
long as you shape them
right right because you need to be be
careful to recognize as you said there's
boundaries that
you know i can't lie to a tree i
definitely can't lie to a forest fire
forest fires don't care about the words
i say and the problem of taking reality
like you loop it back you
you internalize and metabolize too much
of reality as being a human phenomenon
so you don't actually get a felt sense
of the boundaries of lying which is
pretty funny um
and then you know i guess if i can if i
can take that and kind of loop it all
away from the from the bottom you say oh
yes and by the way
humanness is also a forest right the
the basis of the systems of
justification
are sitting on top of a more
natural systems of coordinated behavior
to use your language right
and if i if i lie so vigorously as to
disrupt the underlying
basis of communication of justification
at all
then i've really done myself a
disservice because i am what is called
that's the technical term it's a
technical term so i'd like to talk about
us as humans we are humans who are
primates and people
okay so you know we're the embedded
primates
and then we built this person culture
layer of justification that we socialize
our children into
um but that's all that's the force
that's growing on top of our
primate world all right so in a
uh let's just just reset
and let's go back to just sorry what do
we mean by systems of justification
right um it's a good i mean this concept
of justification the way i use has lots
of different
flavors and meanings so uh but systems
then
are network systems uh of
legitimizing is an ought
basically okay so the word paradigm
the propositional networks of paradigms
would be systems of justification
okay so is an ought or or what is true
and what is
good exactly right okay and there's
there's a holding
of some kind of uh sort of network i'm
almost seeing almost like a matrix
which of course is a high dimensional
network that allows a particular
i guess now utterance right because they
were in language space
utterance to be positioned in terms of
its
value of truth and its value of
good uh-huh yeah exactly i i i
think i may have mentioned that this was
this question exactly this question
was my uh my thesis at harvard i worked
on this piece
uh so it's interesting as you're saying
it i'm actually like in the back of my
mind trying to dust off the ways that i
thought about it
whatever it was 20 years ago nice we are
coordinated so it's this
you know i have a i have an argument
and my argument is a modulation of
three things one is as you say the the
embedding
the embedding of a series of utterances
in a system of justification which is
trying to create as much value as
possible
and trying to make as true and good or
valuable uh right argument prop set of
propositions as i can put forward
yep and then and then one is the
groundingness of it right the degree to
which the truth
the epistemological framework of our
system of justification
loops back right because there's always
a bit of a checksum on the truth side
yep you know um whatever you do
don't do that because a lion's about to
eat you the line over there dude oh
my argument just fell to pieces
and then the third so the third piece is
then of course there's the counter
arguments there's a whole of
other modulations of clusters of
propositions that are
are balancing you know in weight and
there's a sensing of okay we've
our paradigm has found a a
way of weighing these things against
each other
right and then as we do that we come to
a way of saying okay
that that's the thing that has the most
value the most
truth and the most goodness to it and
therefore
exactly exactly and then it's
hierarchically and centrally networked
so some of the unbelievably core things
right that are central to the
justification
system uh peter limberg you know did
that
culture multi-polar culture work yeah
and he
identified all the different paradigms
and he had a wonderful table
where they had the core belief and then
the core antithesis
so who were the good players what are
the core belief that we justify what is
our big
threat okay so that shows sort of this
the systemic
hierarchical structural nature about
what's
central what's proximal to the system
in other words uh another way of looking
at like at james madison university we
have a a mission
statement right so then everything is
going to then
stem out from this value vision
truth statement and then how does it fit
um
and are are you a part of this
system of justification in a particular
way
okay neat so um what i'm what's coming
to me is something along the lines of uh
i can't remember exactly who it is
it's in mathematics but the notion that
i can't construct a higher logic
out of a lower logic that the
instantiation of an axiomatic of a
particular system of justification
creates the boundary conditions of what
it is
like google well you're thinking of well
it's very good alien yeah
very very um there's somebody else more
specific who is talking about
the domain but it's okay that's that's a
good reference to kind of orient the
what what i'm talking about so there's
something like
um you know once i've established
these axiomatics i have i've created a
field of play it's kind of like the
rules of football
or the rules right completely like the
rules of chess exactly
those are the that is isomorphic they
are the same thing
and what's interesting is that okay
there's a lot of things inside the space
and many many different variations of
the game of chess that you can play
but it is also bounded right there
there's
an infinitely large number of things
that are not chess
right uh and so this is this is the
the problem i think the primary problem
that we run into so often
and i guess now in particular it's kind
of a running up against it which is that
oh how funny the lacunae just fell
into it
right well that well we are in this
unpre-stable space right it's like well
what
ah ah right okay so if i
as a child for example find myself
almost like moving away from the
location that is aware of the notion of
chess
as being just one
axiomatic yep one paradigm
right um and and and and or for example
my language my cultural my
system of justification as being just
a and by definition a finite space in
the context of an
infinite space then i am quite
stuck i'm stuck in two very specific
ways
one is if the moves that i need to make
are outside of the rule set
that i now perceive as obligate and
exhaustive of all possible moves
that i'm going to fail sometimes known
as die
or a lack of fitness
and also um something like
how's this work like two to the degree
to which
there are like in peter lindberg's thing
uh there are built-in antipathies built
in conflicts
um and i'm wondering to the degree which
that's
intrinsic and maybe it is it is let me
i'll explain to you exactly why it's a
very creation
that is that the antithesis is
contingent it's also what you said that
propositional elements open up the void
space all around them okay so when you
make claims and you may then you open up
counter factual space claims
um which is really the root of it all
so um so first let uh
yeah if we want to travel this path a
little bit so obviously you're really
familiar with john and his four
so one aspect of john's frame is this
course is four ps
of knowing okay so we have procedural
knowing
perspectival and participatory these are
all by the way embodied in primates
they have all those p's okay um but they
don't have the fourth p
which is symbolic syntactical
propositional knowing
okay and so the root of this whole idea
that's all part of this unified theory
of knowledge that i built
this is actually the first route of the
entire system
comes in 1996 to 1997 okay
and it has everything to do with the
emergence of propositions
okay so what we are right now
at pre-propositional we're participatory
we have a capacity for shared joint
attention and then we get symbolic
tagging of our objects and verbs so
antelope there okay
and that can create all its coordination
we're probably got fire we probably have
some hunting
but then somebody gets the antelope are
over there
okay the antelope antelope there
all right is an associative coordinative
matrix
okay the antelope are over there
is a declarative propositional statement
all right
now what that does is it opens up the
potential of a question that says how do
you know
maybe they aren't all right
so propositions then set the stage for
the challenge which is the question
you challenge the veracity of the
proposition or its utility
okay so once you have a meaning making
statement now you're making laying claim
to a truth which then opens up
counterfactuals which then can be
pressed
by questions okay
why why is that not also true of just
antelope there
because you you need in order to have
the the cognitive machinery in order you
can certainly navigate that
but you can't engage in veracity truth
claim making that's why
that's why we'll talk about the
fundamental unit of language as a
proposition
because it then makes a semantic truth
claim that can then be challenged
antelope there doesn't have enough
or machinery to make the truth claim
okay unless it's unless it's specified
in relationship
to a particular object field relation
that's communicated
and from my vantage point that's what's
that's what the language acquisition
device of syntax does so so to make the
point very fine the the point is what
you were just saying which is the
the object field yeah so
the notion is that there is a moment at
which
there is a um
a distinct and intentional
um mapping associative
associative mapping to use like
associational
epistemology so the notion is that there
is a way of
uh so prior to that so let's just i'm
going to like
really really zoom in on that because i
feel like that transition is crucial in
fact it is i may even back up another
step
uh but so there's there's a moment
at which you use some really good words
and i'll just ask you to use them again
um utterances
it's coordinated sound making uh
has a well i guess what was the language
what would you use
what's what's what's the what's the well
they have a shared intentionality with a
symbolic reference
you know before before we transition
across the line i say antelope there
right um which i think is akin more to
like
we're singing together yep or or
other animals have very clear symbolic
calls
okay so like certain kinds of squirrels
will have a hawk call
okay and that's different than a snake
call
okay so that but they the other squirrel
can't say oh you're bs and me
ah okay okay okay so it's like it's
almost like a
uh it's more it's more like almost like
a a release of a particular
neurochemical
in your body it is a sign
that is coordinated with a uh
state and it's almost mechanical in that
sense it's like
a shift in my biological and
dispositional state which activates a
particular
expression um and no different than my
pupils dilating when i perceive the
presence of a predator
right so it has that it's it's
participatory
up very grounded participatory up
okay so antelope there is of that sort
meaning that there's no sort of
it may be wrong there may not be an
antelope there but just the same way
that there may not be a hawk in the air
when i perceive it or that my heartbeat
going up because i perceive the lie may
be false
but it's a qualitatively grounded in
that way up
okay exactly exactly so now so so
we get the humans are coordinating and
they have to interact in a behavioral
investment sense with the antelope there
okay
but they are not engaged in
propositional claim
and that what i give rise to then once
you get a proposition you get rise to
the question
answer dynamic okay the question answer
dynamic is the proposition is the answer
then you can question it okay and as
you'll notice with your children
the cocked into machinery of questions
is really not that hard
why dad why why okay
well answer it okay the
answer is actually where a lot of the
machinery comes in okay so once we get
we get this is what's called the tipping
point and the that gives ultimately rise
to the culture person plane of existence
on the tree if not
hold on can i say this so what i'm what
i'm
what i am imagining and this is the
point
what i'm imagining is in fact precisely
the emergence of a shared imaginal space
this is the key move right the key move
is is in the mind
the development of a model of what is
as a it's not necessarily
primary at least extremely important
piece right how your relationship with
reality works
so what happens is when you begin to
have a shared imaginary
yep so i have a model of what's on the
other side of that
wall and and now as we're discussing
propositionally what's happening is that
we are
uh basically updating our models right
what's on the shared
in that mall so it's the emergence of an
imaginal space
that has a quality of reality to shape
my choices
that are distinctly meaningful
in the context of just my my
physical condition and so these two
things are now sitting next to each
other
on the one hand i have my current actual
biological physical
disposition which is responding to the
phenomenon that are going on
right then i also have this mental model
i have this imaginal space
which is is is feeding back on and
changing and shifting and shaping my
my position right so you have these two
things going on which i'm sure that if
we looked at it and
i'm sure you can do this chapter and
verse actually has a strict neurological
correlate i can actually talk
about the prefrontal cortex relationship
the cerebrum into the
linux and this by the way this at an
individual level this is happening
first in the animal evolution so animals
with cortexes are doing this that is
they are
uh unplugging from the immediacy of the
environment and starting to run
simulations about particular
consequences okay
and then what we can do what the human
can do almost certainly as a unique
primate before we're verbal
is that we can intuit and generate
shared attentional
space okay so we can actually engage in
an
implicit inter subjectivity that starts
this process okay all right so now
before we have propositional knowledge
we can intuit that i'm pointing i'm
gesturing
you've got engage in mimicry you can
track my body i point over there you
intuitively know i'm looking over there
that's a that's a real talent that we
have and now this is creating this
inter-subjective space
okay okay and then we start symbolically
tagging the objects and ver
and changes in terms of nouns and
verbs not but it's not syntactical yet
so it's just a tag
okay and now all of a sudden our systems
really start to come online
all right and boom then we get a
language acquisition device
where that symbol gets then organized
sequentially in towards a kind of
recursive syntax okay then you get
propositional
now you get a highway of information
that not only has the shared imaging but
can now create
propositional layering of that shared
imaginative and that
that thing is going to actually then
create a feedback loop
because you get a question answer
dynamic okay
and what this does and just to be clear
my understanding as i'm listening to you
that the question answer dynamic has to
do with something like running a
checksum
on the propositional machinery that is
generating the
integer subjective space right as i just
did
right then exactly i just i just
basically ran a question
i didn't put a question mark at the end
of it but i just proposed this question
you said yes
click click check sum interest objective
space has now got some degree of
validation
exactly we're building a system of
justification now together
yep okay
all right
all right cool okay so
let me put i'm going to put this in in
the field of conversation
it's not going to show up yet but think
of it like the uh
what's that trope like somebody's gun
chekhov's gun it's just this is
chekhov's gun
in our conversation all right i was just
like literally
whatever 20 wow it's been 21 minutes man
that was intense 22 minutes ago was on a
conversation with jimmy wheel and zack
stein a couple of the folks were in it
one of the things that came up was a a
notion
that the emergence of language that it
goes it goes uh
singing predates speaking
uh that that that pre-linguistic humans
for example
had this omni uh
bird call like we could we could we
could emulate animal sounds in a
generalized fashion we could do the
squirrel sound and do the bird sound
um and had extremely high sensitivity to
tonal matching and harmonics and so
you can imagine these sort of like bands
of humans going around like
singing and singing together
creates a felt sense of community you're
not part of something and i saw that
what i call the gestural rhythm
that's going to precede uh propositional
language
yeah okay cool so so you know for
anybody who happens to be watching this
in the mindset in addition to this you
know
this frame that i was putting forward to
kind of
make my own sense of what of your of the
transition is that in the
pre-propositional state
there's a music of the spheres like
there's this
deeply connected sense of harmony and
interplay
which is primary and a very very felt
sense of that and it means
truly acoustically right there's a bird
spawn but it's now harmonic okay
so now we begin then we transition over
the we we
leave eden we transition over into this
new place which has this entire field
this entire
meal you of possibility and as is always
the case you've just opened up a can of
worms
right there's lots of moves that can be
made inside propositional space and as
you say by the time you're four
you discover a crucial one which is
known as lie
that's right well you made a very
important point about eaton by the way
just so that
people are following because this all
fits in exactly what i'm
trying to convey with a whole tree of
knowledge is that we fall out of eden
as a function of propositional knowledge
and self-consciousness
okay so like we wake up to the paradise
and then we name it and we call it good
and evil and we name ourselves in the
process and all of a sudden we're like
oh my
god cover up and we're going to die
because we have that capacity now
through this kind of cognitive machinery
and inter-subjective dialogue space
to generate a whole host of other
adjacent possibles it just opens up a
radically
way exactly so so nice all right so if i
kind of zoom in on it
if i take a look at the notion of lie
it's funny i actually remember having a
class
like creative writing class and and uh i
i'm i'm not sure if this is true i'm
gonna lie but the story is good
which is that the professor actually had
a bottle of bourbon on his desk like at
a university
and he had a southern accent he's like a
southern writer and he said you know my
my people are natural liars which makes
us really good
storytellers all right so the point
there is something along the lines of
this thing that we call lying is first
and foremost
this notion of iterating possibilities
right in interest objective space right
of course extremely powerful right if i
can start as i'm doing right now
right i'm perturbating the possibility
space by uttering a whole bunch of
justifications
a series of propositions that hang
together according to our
epistemological and moral or
ethical schema and and we're playing
with them
you know right einsteinian thought uh
experiments
which is a lot easier than trying to
engage in
you know iterative practical testing on
empirical grounds like physical ground
and i can benefit from the fact that
you and i can play this game in fact
remotely you could be thousands of miles
away we're still playing the game and we
could roll other people into it
and so the the is called exploring this
space is just impossible
so if one of the primary pruning rules
or primary filtering mechanisms of
adaptive fitness
is the capacity to simultaneously expand
the adjacent possible and search the
adjacent possible and i think both are
crucial
absolutely um then this thing
clearly right once you start playing
that game then you've just
exited this is why it's a it's a it's a
clear line like it's a
phase transition what do you call it you
call it a junction or a joint point
a joint joint between animal mind to
culture person
yeah and that's why we're no longer apex
predators as daniel
schmuckenberger often talks about we we
we change the rules of the game
because we can accelerate because of the
intergenerational transmission of
knowledge
and the accumulation of that creates
cultural evolution
which now means we're on a different
acceleratory curve
in the way in which we're navigating so
we can beat the you know
end up dominating everywhere we go right
right
yeah the the guys that i talked to at
the santa fe institute i think called
that a portal pathway
which is the same well if you see it on
the on the it's a hole in fact the
fifth joint point is a portal pathway
into the digital i mean each one of them
is a portal pathway
that then elicits a variation selection
retention complexity building feedback
loop that's mediated through information
processing communication systems
and boom gives rise to a whole new plane
of the possible
yeah okay so let's go there so we could
we could know we we sat
for a moment at the emergence of systems
of justification
and we've kind of got a little bit of a
handle on what's up there together like
now we're
getting into this shared space and we
can kind of
fast forward so now we've got cultural
evolution you know right step one
humans exit the role of apex predator
and or start playing a totally different
game
step two they start playing that game
against each other we can focus on that
if we'd like
right um and maybe game a yeah
exactly game a that's right exactly um
and then and then we enter into where we
are now
right which is we're reaching the the
end of that
phase into that exact stage so okay
what's so let's talk about that so you
talked about the digital
so let's do the same thing let's zoom
into the the tail end
of the culture game and then
the emergence of the new thing exactly
okay
so um let's at least let's ground
ourselves about where we
are so we can have a nice frame for what
we can be talking about what's very
difficult to talk about given
what we don't know is coming right um so
so in the tree of knowledge the tree of
knowledge says following matter
life mind and culture are such radically
different planes of existence
okay because what emerges is a
coordinating system
of information processing and
communication networks
that coordinate the flow of energy to
give rise to more and more
complex structure yep okay
so cells store information rna dna
they they process that inside their
lipid membrane and then communicate with
each other
okay then you jump up to animals and
nervous systems yoke cells together
coordinate the animal of the hole and
then animals communicate to each other
okay then when we started jiving
in our gestural symbolic way and then
linked into propositions created the
inner subjective language highway
that yoked our subjective minds together
to create the culture person plane
okay so the medium to marshall mcluhan
the medium is absolutely
central right and ever since we started
writing so what we started to do with
writing
we started to create an externalized
memory
of our symbolic language okay so we
externalized our memory
and then we stored that and created
better and better systems
so that other people could then process
that when they learned how to read
and develop printing presses and then we
developed computational systems on
quantitative things like an abacus
and then turned that into a babbage
thinking machine all right
and then in the 20th century we
developed the silicon chip we developed
the internet
we developed artificial intelligence and
can yoke them together
what does that all mean we have created
a whole new information processing
system in communication
network okay out of material culture
so we built all these material cultural
things our technologies
but now we've created an independent or
at least interfacing
artificial intelligence network so now
there is
information processing communication
taking place in just a radically
different way
that's my term you know many people use
the term digital
okay so the digital so now
that's why the tree of knowledge says
very clearly we're going to be in a flux
point
okay it's like it's like we it's like
what happened when we just discovered
propositions we have now just discovered
digital and yoking digital and
interfacing with digital
and creating the whole digital
interconnected internet
so we're on the cusp where we were at
the fourth joint point we're now on the
cusp of the fifth
and we're now just opening up like we
use propositions now we're opening up
digital interface spaces okay so
something like we discover the
interest objective space and we begin
exploring how to do it good
yep and we notice that there's a number
of basic boundary conditions
right one boundary condition is how much
intersubjective space can you hold
yep if i'm limited to the boundaries of
human memory
there's a certain limit to the amount of
intersubjective space that can be
can be generated right therefore
we begin the process of trying to
cybernetically enhance
memory and we discover that if we
externalize
memory into physical reality
writing then we have expanded that
capacity and therefore can build much
larger inter-subjective spaces which as
you say also requires the
creation of new particular skills and
capacities like literacy
and probably cognitive structures for
being able to do
translations between languages and being
able to
run higher level abstractions to verify
the
epistemology has to get stronger as you
start having more ambiguity built into
the symbolic structure just trying to
map the inner subjective space
we also have notions about velocity like
as you said in distance
right if the only way for me to read the
book is i've got to travel to milan by
wagon
that's you know it's a it slows down the
ability for us to share the new
subjective space which is basically the
end of the day a bandwidth issue
so if i can ramp up the bandwidth by
virtue of being able to call somebody or
talk with somebody
or if i can just do a video call over
zoom the velocity of information
exchange goes way up
so i can now in the in the context of
digital
we're reaching something along the lines
of a
it feels like it's it's interesting to
think about the quantitative qualitative
shift at the quantitative level
so on this side of the transition it's
just like
moore's law like the thing we've been
doing for 70
000 years we're just doing more of it
faster
lots and lots and lots so memory is
expanding like doubling every year
remember that
yep and velocity is increasing and the
number
of interactions that can happen is
increasing and the reification capacity
to do the
checksum at the epistemological level is
increasing in spite of the false news
fake news problem which we're going to
probably have to get to in this
conversation
then you've got this notion of
qualitative shift
and that's where things get real tricky
right right that implies something which
is not the same as
person right and not the same as culture
no all of person and all of culture live
below the line
so whatever we're talking about on the
other side of the line ain't person and
it ain't culture
yep right so that and that is
so you have a novel information
processing system and the way a silicon
chip processes information right and
then we
build so now our what i mean we used to
have you know
rocks hammers build houses but now we
build things that actually
process information computers on their
own right
and then they get more and more learning
mechanisms and then they get more
interface we call that artificial
intelligence of course
and and whether it's artificial
intelligence on its own like ray
kurzweil thinks
or like i think which is really going to
be artificial intelligence interfacing
with human intelligence
and as our human capacity increases and
we
neural link as elon musk was talking you
know
we build the information processing of
our capacity to plug into the internet
okay um uh it just the opening
of that interface is
like we're like jellyfish right before
they got brains
you know you got a distributed neural
net right
and then you've got a control center
system and then boom all of a sudden you
can move the whole goddamn system
so we have distributed and it's getting
more and more centralized
and whatever that tipping point is going
to be is going to launch us into the
digital
and that's what we're staring at here at
the 21st century this is that's why the
blue church is so inadequate because
it's built on radically different
information processing communication
sense making systems that are now
inadequate to manage uh what we've
opened up
right and i think we can actually begin
the process of making
fundamental statements of what adequate
looks like
yeah i think that's where things get
interesting we can actually start
defining the parameter space it's like
look
i don't know what's going to be on the
other side of that line but i know for
sure it's going to have to have this set
of parameters
exactly and i'm not sure i'll go ahead
okay i was just talking with a
philosophical friend
we were talking about well we can't know
what it is but he used the
uh analogy well we can midwife it okay
that is that we can put constraints on
it and then we can think about
what is adequate to see coming down the
pike and how to hold it in a way so that
chaos and order and and framings are
structured well there's a simple one
right i can give you one very simple
parameter
if it if if it if it kills everybody
then it's outside of the parameter space
i think we can start there
right if it results in the extinction of
all life
outside of the parameters certainly our
perimeter space but that's actually the
point there is actually i think that
let's drill deeper on that because i
think that this uh
there's something deeper there yeah
absolutely when we were
and and exiting eden is is the hint
right so there was a that we had a
moment where we had this
uh this thing that was coming up
that had to use john's language it was
at level participatory knowing
right relevance realization something
that is grounded all the way down
to 13 billion years of evolution right
all the way down with continuity
right no discontinuity then we have this
leaving of eden
which has a discontinuity and we somehow
exit that to come into propositional
space
which is a different kind of thing right
then
and the two are you know you're you're
as you said you're you're a primate
you're still a primate
and you're a person but there's a
discontinuity between person and primate
and we try to keep them linked sometimes
sometimes we don't sometimes we engage
in all kinds of crazy in person
space that is absolutely out of
alignment with our primates
nature which generally makes us unhappy
in the long term but might make us happy
in the short term
tell ourselves lies like crazy um
so
the proposition that
that digital that total that that set of
digital that
extinguishes all life is outside the
parameter space
is another way of saying that the
discontinuity
between the propositional and the
participatory
is outside the parameter space that the
digital
must must of necessity
be connected must be in continuity
with the whole evolutionary story
exactly exactly so and that's why i like
to call it
the digital metacultural transcendent
okay what i hope for and what i mean by
that is
the constraints of the emerging digital
okay need to be connected to the root
from metacultural down into cultural
into mind into life
yeah and you know and and the wise way
if we do it wisely we open up heaven
and if we do it right and that's the and
that's the
you know and by the way that's the whole
metaphor of from the tree of knowledge
into the garden
okay is a return to the garden
all right uh that allows for
if we get it right if we get it wisely
done
um we can align across and
and return to paradise all right so
check it so this is you you mentioned
kurzweil and by saying kurzweil i'm just
going to kind of invoke an entire
uh category of
of thinking of systems of justification
earlier i think actually even the very
beginning of the conversation we talked
about the notion of say
chess which
is it was an example of the notion of
paradigm or system of justification
and we already did the we already did
the
the thing we said hey here's the
challenge here's the problem
if i put on my system of justification
and take it as the whole of reality
remember the technical term yeah
yeah
because no system of justification
can have the full complexity
of actual reality and
it has built into it an entire set
of conflicts and blind spots
and commitments that have that are
themselves
unjustifiable it's it's not going to be
up to the task
right so in the move to digital the move
to digital cannot
come at the behest of or
through any system of justification
because all systems of justification are
equivalently lacking in this exact
way exactly exactly and this gets right
back actually to the kind of sensibility
that we need
we need some sort of trans-paradigmatic
ability
right that i do think need some sort of
meta guiding point but there is a uh
there is a way in which we need to
realize that we need to jump above
our normal paradigmatic way and
certainly to try to take a paradigmatic
way and to try to impose it upon
uh the digital is a guaranteed
right guaranteed and it's funny i
mean
we can we can dance around that and if
anybody feels like we need to we can
double click on it but the word
i agree with you i completely agree with
you guaranteed
and just kind of threw a little bit
there it's it's the same
degree of guaranteed that thermodynamics
makes
in a closed system all right once i've
closed the system
it's just a matter of time before all
free energy is
gone and i reach a level of of entropic
equilibrium
which we call guaranteed for the
point of view of anything that wants to
continue to live
right exactly we need that free energy
rate flow in order to have our
organization if we
lose constraints we're going to be
doomed so
okay so that's there's some good stuff
there so the question that might be
something like
a couple of things come up right so one
has to do with a
like a is the trans what's the
relationship between the
trans-paradigmatic and the
pre-paradigmatic
i thought there's something useful there
right oh yeah we don't want to
fall into the pre-paradigmatic because
that's not very helpful we went through
the whole paradigmatic that was a lot of
work a lot of people died let's
let's make that useful sure but there's
something about the transparent that is
akin
to the pre-paradigm right right
so maybe we can just talk about what is
the transparent maybe that's maybe a key
piece to focus on
right so it depends on sort of the
perspective so let's go let's keep going
with this since we've been talking about
kids
okay so kids come in and they
internalize and they have a
in a classic piaget way they're sort of
pre-paradigmatic
okay at the age of three four they can
bring their logical systems to a
particular
point all right but they're not
operating from them systematically
okay uh they don't they don't run from
situation to situation
by the time they get to seven and eight
and start to believe what mom and dad
believe
okay they start to internalize mom and
dad's paradigm
which is seen as god you know that's
just what's true
right okay and then they have
the adolescent break right
and they're basically like wait a minute
there's out other space outside of these
paradigms mom and dad maybe you made
that stuff
up okay and then you get the who says
how do you why do you say why don't i
say
okay that's the adolescent individuation
point
where you know depending on course on
the cognitive complexity of the
adolescent and the parents and
everything else but
the way it plays so now you get into
adulthood where adulthoods are trying to
negotiate
the paradigm and we used to sit in
systems that would have
a general stable paradigm across
okay so you know middle ages for a heck
of a long time in europe
is christian paradigm right that's what
everybody had
but as you and john were talking about
that other time and we came back and
looped in
the parent the justification systems of
understanding relative to the actual
techno changes that are happening
right it's just i mean so information
chaos
okay so what what i would say and want
to say is all right well let's well what
comes after the adult well in my model
then the sage
okay so the sage is then if we go to
wilbur what is wilbur saying when he
talks about trans versus pre
right so the trans versus pre is that
sometimes the trans will say what the
pre does but they say it from very
different places
right so the sage might say hey you know
let's think carefully about black lives
matter okay
and just like a pre-rational kind of
understand non-understanding person says
i hate that stuff
okay but the critic of the sage versus
the rejecting of sort of a narrow white
mentality
okay might say the same thing but from
radically different perspectives
okay so that's a tree make sure you know
where that's
trans versus pre that's wilbur's whole
point even though they might
and and versus convention yeah
right okay so so the inside the culture
person plane
we want to cultivate a sage
capacity which in my estimation would be
hey you need to to rise above the
abstractions of all the paradigms to see
across them
okay to hold what's integrated across
them and appreciate their pluralistic
and have some coherence in that
okay so now let's talk about it why is
now the trans in some ways now like the
pre well if we go into the digital world
right now we go up a level and we're in
this
space now we're the new kids on the
block i mean whatever would be
on the back side of this we're we're the
infants i mean that's why
i so appreciated you and daniel would
talk well first thing you got to know is
you don't know anything now
right we're back to sort of socrates or
whatever it's just sort of like
huh you know so now now we're on we're
in phase
another phase and we got to bring this
consciousness to it but also realize
on the back side of this thing um
they're going to be stuff
going on that we at 100 years from now
we can't even fathom
is that chad yeah yeah yeah so what it
activated me was i thought myself
it's funny maybe we should just have
this as a rule if if in doubt jazz
um which was so i was thinking about
that developmental process and i was
kind of invoking zach right because so
zack stein
sure oftentimes development comes up in
conversation
right he always tells me i'm
underdeveloped
[Applause]
and i was like well we can talk well
because it's always true yeah hey
i'll take that um
right okay so let's slow this down so
adolescents adults adults in
relationship with each other
at least a piece of that in the way that
you're telling the story has to do with
the notion of
who has authorship
over the axiomatics
in the paradigm right so we have we have
two big moves i think it's important to
kind of hold these
one move is the running of the paradigm
per se this is uh
if you're in the game is everybody
playing the game and it has the notions
of fairness like did we violate the
rules that kind of stuff
then the other move is the is the actual
authorship of the paradigm
i think where people get lost oftentimes
many of the languages that we use like
say like sovereignty
or authority have to do with that second
move
yep definitely you know certainly if i'm
looking at it from a high enough level
i'm like well
whoever makes the rules is definitely in
the best position to win the game
right so i don't really care about uh
how we play the game if i get to be the
one who makes the rules
and that's kind of that's what's
happening in that adolescent moment
right the adolescent is like well hold
on now
i can see the fact that there's
something going on here
and i can and i notice by the way that i
can challenge the rules
so they're not real right they're not
kind of like this magic thing that i
can't challenge
and then there's okay what does that
look like how do i get into it now if i
drop into a pre mode
right but now i'm in the indigenous so
if i'm in the indigenous
systems of justification the adults
are interacting with each other still
very held
by the participatory
revolutionary context right because if
if you defect on the tribe we're all
kind of going to die
fast feedback loops on that kind of a
thing so the
notion of who gets to make the rules is
is is pretty is sort of distributed by
necessity right anybody who tries to and
and probably at that point the
consciousness of the skillfulness of
being able to take
of of steering the ship by driving the
paradigm
probably wasn't particularly rich i
wasn't like
no whereas these days of course it is no
so
you've got that right now what happens
though as we move forward in the culture
game
the that that becomes the currency
ever it becomes the battlefield right
right i can i can fight the fight of
like
uh having a particular position inside a
paradigm
but increasingly it becomes obvious to
anybody who's worth the salt
the only move that matters is the one
who's actually authoring paradigms
cultureware 2.0 right
i can be in one of peter lindberg's
boxes but then i'm just kind of like
i'm a player in somebody else's game or
i could be creating the box
and the fighting is now going on at that
level right and this
forensic conflict because there is no
meta paradigm
that can imperially distribute justice
which is just to say systems of
justification
across all paradigms because at any
point i can instantiate another paradigm
which does not accept the axiomatics of
that paradigm and we're stuck
right there you go and we're stuck now
in in and i guess you know this is
against the postmodernists
not it like they were correct that right
all sitting still on top of just
nature right in nature the law of tooth
and claw
predates the system of justification
um okay so that's all there so we end up
we end up with that as a as an
acknowledgement as a recognition
now when you speak to the notion of the
sage who's going beyond the adult
first of all the sage is aware of this
right
and one of the things they have
metacognitive awareness it's okay so you
can base it i
am a justifier huh and i was situated in
a justification
huh i wonder what that is i can now
empathize that other people were too
now i can consider this how do i know my
position's right
you know the the socrates that all i
mean his
i would argue that socrates really finds
formal epistemology
okay and the socratic method is the
realization that we built these systems
of justification just on
pragmatic convention right and then he
is he thinks about it in terms of
mathematics and then looks at our logic
system is like
yeah no we're just basically bsing right
that's why i didn't know anything all of
a sudden that's right
i poked literally just twice and
realized there was nothing but right it
was all just a bunch of bs
it's like oh my god they were building
these pyramids to show that they had
control
right but actually it was just a
performative act to gain control and
then they would be on top of it and then
they could legitimize it but it wasn't
it wasn't axiomatic at the level of
pythagoras theorem that's deductive it
was more
social convention bs so what is
underneath social convention bs
well that's formal philosophy in the
west really has been asking that
question ever since it's been basically
and it's been confused out of its mind
right because it didn't understand that
actually it's trapped inside the process
of justification
you know it doesn't it does it can the
nice thing about what i
when i went insane is when i was like oh
my god i'm seeing this as a psychologist
i'm like oh my god we're all a bunch of
justifiers
including socrates we're trapped inside
that right except we we still have that
primate right right well right on top of
that right
we have realization which is which is
the so this is like the
return the resolution to the meeting
crisis that john proposes
hey guys check it out it's okay yes oh
k
you don't have to rely exclusively
on systems of justification to make
meaning
to figure out what to do we've actually
got this 13
billion year old machinery that's been
working
across the history of all things right
that's
that's the the iceberg underneath this
tiny little novelty that just
popped into existence in the universe
that really can't do the thing you're
asking it to do that's why i call this
verbals
[Laughter]
okay yeah verbals or primate verbal
right
obviously it rhymes with gerbil that let
us know that we're chattering up here
right on top of our primate system and
we got to pay attention how to align
that thing
not just try to fantasize in some
autistic way about how we could analyze
our way out of this thing
back to it right and i think that's
exactly right the fantasize in some
autistic way
double click that group of folks who
want to do this thing
i'm tagging as kurzweil who want to do
this thing
separate from relevance realization no
just illogical just randomize the
process if
you're if you're of that type i would
invite you to just think it through
like right just think very clearly about
all the different things we were just
talking about
you will arrive at the conclusion that
that's actually illogical
it's actually a bad idea it can you can
formally prove
that it cannot work therefore
some alternative approach is necessary
and we can propose
what an alternative approach looks like
which is first and foremost to
re-stitch the continuity between
relevance realization
and propositional structures right that
exiting of eden
the discontinuity first and foremost
that has to be brought back into
continuity and it's not that complicated
right it's a way of being able to
reactivate well
yeah it's actually not complicated it's
just hard because we spent 50 000 years
extinguishing capacities
but and really intensely over the past
several hundred years and
right well once we develop civilization
but if we develop the cities in just the
right way
somebody yeah like
you know get school gone
right just get rid of that um which
doesn't mean by the way we aren't
thoughtful about how we
promote development oh god right
machinery that was sort of copied from
the prussians
not the right way to do this it's just a
bad idea right you want to rewind rewind
not more more more which is crazy it
drives me nuts right whenever we run
into a problem we're like
well how about more of this stuff that
is terrible oh my god
how about none of it and then do
something different can we
escape from that paradigmatic trap well
this is what the hope is
is the hope is that with the right
insights of course zach go back to zack
stein of course in
not only educa development but education
right we need the right
teacherly authority to manage the right
intergenerational transmission of
information
in the right way if we are going to go
through if we're going to midwife this
thing
yeah right and and this is a nightmare
for us
this is unbelievably complicated if we
don't get the parameters right
why because the world is changing so
fast and the paradigms are so outdated
right that the kids are looking back to
us and saying you guys are you guys
don't know anything
right right right and at one level
they're right
of course but then they're very
vulnerable you know all of a sudden i
just
i was talking about yeah i spent three
hours a day uh in the last three days on
on tick tock i was like what i was like
oh yeah
i was like you know and it's like you
know you do have something to learn from
dad about like
wisdom and depth and connecting to
wisdom traditions right you know
it's like we need to have something and
not spending three days on tick tock
and that's why you're three days on peak
talk it's just not all right so
so let's let's let's do it for real it's
like actually do the thing
um all right i'm gonna throw two things
out i can but they're really vague right
now but i think i can i can get them out
okay so the one that's gonna come later
has to do with the
the protocols the metacognitive
protocols or the protocols of
transparent culture
something like that yep got it
all right and then and then here the
thing that's going to come first
is something like what is this parity
transparent
mind i suppose we'll just put some words
about that
uh what's it about what's the thing
all right now if we if we if we say okay
and i like that idea of demoralizing or
humiliating paragraphs just take them
off their
their perch let's just call them games
i've got
i've got kind of you know the
enlightenment era game
cool i've got a medieval um
islamic golden age game cool right i can
kind of it can
identify a bunch of games and i can say
okay each one of these games is
a system of justification that has some
set of axiomatics
um and you know a series of
epistemological
and uh ethical or moral actually moral
epistemological and moral
um evaluating functions the position and
proposition inside that space that's
what
we're talking about um okay cool
now now what i'm gonna do is i'm gonna
say like
two or three things and it actually
starts to get pretty simple so what i'm
gonna say is those games are tools
they're a means to an end um
they're not an end in themselves and
they're certainly not the whole story
so what a transparent mind
is good at is creating and it's
instantiating paradigms
it's like it's like a it's a it's like a
good artisan right an artisan is not a
hammer machine
an artisan is an artisan madison deals
with the phenomenon in front of her
has access to being able to notice when
a particular tool is the right tool for
the job
and also maintains the capacity to
design
bespoke a tool you know the idea of a
jig
the idea that jig is a great metaphor if
you do have any woodwork it's like hey
i need to build a tool to do the thing
like i can kind of try to struggle my
way through by
shoehorning a bunch of tools i mean yes
you can use a screwdriver as a hammer if
you've got to
but maybe a hammer is the right thing to
do right so that that ability to
actually say i am not my tools
i am the author of the tools and to
anchor yourself
in that location which is our humanness
right we have that we are that thing
which gave rise to paradigms
we are not the paradigm and so to build
a archer's tree
a skillfulness right able to discern
which tools which paradigms right
are appropriate for the things that i'm
engaged in
and when in fact it's necessary or
useful to craft
new ones bespoke in the context that i
find myself in
that sounds like a really good
description of wisdom as far as i'm
concerned
yeah yeah so the wisdom and artistry
right which
would be something like the the right
judgment right right
skillful creation exactly and i love the
metacognitive
you know shift uh that layer of
self-reflective awareness that allows
you to step
outside the ocean that you're in and see
the water
yeah water your beliefs and then relate
to that in in a healthy way not in a
freakout way
in a healthy way in a healthy way that
that orients you toward valued states of
being
and does so skillfully with aptness and
reminder reminder
when you're outside of the paradigm
you're not adrift
you're actually sitting on top of 13
billion years of relevance realization
and that's actually that's the tool for
the
the capacity that is the capacity that
is most appropriate
to design to novelty to being in
relationship with complexity this is
sort of
tysonic perches key messages hey guys is
that
knowing right is more better
at dealing with complexity than
paradigms are
paradigms are really good at optimizing
for certain stuff
but they don't deal with complexity
right okay right so so
uh i'll just so with uh lean and rachel
anderson
you know in her book modern
metamodernity all right and we
mesh this with justification systems
theory so
her angle on metamodernism is there are
four major sensibilities oral indigenous
okay pre-modern formal modern
scientific liberal democratic and
post-modern okay
and they each have a particular kind of
sensibility ethos
you know logic right so you know when i
when i what are the rules of my house
how do i relate to my kids and my wife
that's oral indigenous right we make
those things together we embody them
together we decide
you know then there's a mythos ethos at
some level
okay that we need to reference which
would what is the religion that's not a
religion and the role that that's going
to play
right we need to have a logical
structure that does allow us some truth
claims about the objective nature
modernism does that pretty well
post-modernism critiques the danger in
which that
maybe gets empowered and then
legitimizes as a hegemony
right which is there and reminds us
there is no one stance
to have and the trans-paradigmatic
position would be
some way of including and transcending
those and place them aptly in
the time between worlds that we find
ourselves and
and going forward we'll find ourselves
in
really so so then let's flip to the
notion the protocols because because we
in some sense we were just describing
subjective space so let's talk about
inter-subjective space
right and
i like the idea of protocol because at
least it reminds me of you know in the
internet there are protocols
that they facilitate communication they
do not dictate what happens inside the
communication
they put constraints
some simple ones
sorry actually let me back up a little
bit i want to put something in there
so one of the things i was noticing as
you were going through that last little
bit
was um nietzsche i think actually
noticed this
first that a lot of the the
the demoralization of postmodernists
and that shows up a lot in kind of the
poor kids who are subjected to
postmodernism
without any context is
you know if i if i if i spend millennia
um up your relevance realization
system
in favor of optimizing your system of
justification system
and then i take away your system of
you may be you may be forgiven
for falling far on the stack
right for becoming an evilist right yes
oh well i guess it just comes down to
straight
physical violence you're like well no
actually no
there's actually an enormous amount of
getting along that happens
pre-linguistically
we don't need propositions to to
harmonize
in fact they're not even very functional
for that they're really
getting interested just watching newborn
and his mother
you know right with eye contact and you
see a participatory attachment dance
that doesn't have a proposition in it
right right you know so so kind of so
the first hint is to say hey
um you know sorry by the way for all of
us we're all forgiven because we're all
participating in it and all subjected to
it
don't you know all right well you know
do over
um and it's far enough back right the
exit from medium is far enough back you
can't really point to anybody in
particular
uh and and i should say by the way it
sort of had to happen
it was just it's part of the story it's
part of the natural arc thing it's no
different than a lightning bolt i mean
okay so but here we are um
and you know we're faced with a
uh a remembering or a re-skilling
and say okay there's a uh we've kind of
been d
we've been in the matrix we i think
we've used this metaphor before like
we've been in the matrix
now we're out of the matrix and we're
sort of this floppy body that doesn't
have muscle tone
yep fair enough that's where we are but
it's actually not that insanely hard
because for a sizable arc of a
developmental environment we actually
were building the core stuff
and you know by the time as you say by
the time you're four five six seven
you actually have got you know all the
things i needed to learn live i knew
before kindergarten
you got some of the basic stuff so you
sort of return back that child's mind
children are actually decently
functional in relevance realization so
you've got it
you just have to kind of like be okay
with with building it up from there and
building skillfulness
and i like this notion of artistry and
so our job is to actually develop
develop an
artistry in this transparent location
this is i'm talking about
intersubjective space absolutely
i'm there so what i what i what i want
is the net notion of the
like omni jazz where you know i bring my
whole package
yep everything i've got into the
encounter with you
and you bring everything you've got into
the encounter with me but we're in the
transparent medic space it's like i
don't know what's gonna happen here
it could be anything i think actually
game is not predefined
right but what what is present is the
protocols for producing games
right one protocol is be an artist and
build increasing skillfulness in the
ambient
hominid primate gift that is yours and
practice
paradigmatic play and drop in and out of
paradigm shift and modify them play with
them notice how they work you got to get
good at it this is a thing it's a skill
get
good at it and notice how your relevance
realization machinery is
just like playing music you can vibe
with the direction that is moving the
right way like you know that it's there
you just can't say it until you've
actually got the skillfulness of getting
the words to match the feelings right
it's
just like music it's just it is art it's
not just like art it is art that's what
art
is if you've ever written poetry you're
very clear on the notion of how you do
it right the order first is you have a
felt sense then you very carefully
allow the words to move until they land
such that the proposition resonates
with the felt sense that's poetry
so that's the idea become skillful go
ahead right well this is exactly what
um i mean i didn't know i was doing at
the time but so
you know my quest for all of this starts
was i learned to do psychotherapy
okay so i started doing psychotherapy as
a doctoral student
actually as master assume and this
really started to click um
and i could drop into paradigms like
behavioral paradigm
cognitive paradigm freudian paradigm
mystic paradigm you get it right
and watch the experts play with that
and see how they did it and then watch
the lousy ones right
and then i had a pretty good gift that i
could empathize with that and pull that
paradigm on and see the world
through family systems or behavioral or
whatever right
and then bounce around uh and be like
yeah well
hey all of these things make sense and
the idea that we're trying to race
horses against them
right you know that you know like
compete and say oh family systems is the
best you come to my program and learn
that and behaviorism is the best it's
like
that's just not no you know so uh
and it's like so anyway just and that of
course psychotherapy is fundamentally
about
how you relate to people so i'm saying
is that in a particularly sort of
uh salient example it's like yeah you
can actually jump into paradigms
and play with them you know and learn
how to speak the different ones and
relate participatory and indigenous ways
with people as you do
and we've been sold a bill of good that
your whole identity has to be these
propositional paradigms and if you step
outside of them you're betraying them
somehow
yes that village is crucial right and
that's i'm gonna double click on that
just to make sure it
gets the right kind of bias it's like
hey you are not a person
or more specifically you are not an
identity right
totally more vastly vastly more in fact
infinitely more but we will not get
there just yet
crucial right to the degree to which you
are struggling to
sort of valorize your identity i get it
right you definitely don't want to have
a
have your identity be devalorized but
you are not your identity
because your identity is a manifestation
of a context of a particular culture
which just say it's
it's a piece of a paradigm and we're now
transparatigmatic man so you can
actually play and so
this is um my version of what you just
said was actually
i i i discovered dungeons and dragons in
second grade
right so the time where my my sort of
cultural paradigm hadn't really settled
in
i was introduced to a world building
role-playing game
which was cool and i was obsessive so i
and i didn't just stick to that game i
started realizing you could actually get
all kinds of games so i started getting
other games they were in different
milieu like some were science fiction
some were different variations on
fantasy what i noticed was that
you know each one was composed of a set
of basic rules
right basic rules involved how do you
create your character what's your person
then was how do you navigate your
characters moving through the
intersubjective model of reality which
is essentially your culture space right
those are the two
two structures and um and then of course
what happens of course that that insight
could not be lost as i was interacting
with
the role-playing game that we call our
culture right
i was like oh okay so basically this is
just a really shitty game that for some
reason i'm obligated to play
all right and that was like like an
insight probably like in fourth grade
because of that developmental context
absolutely um
okay so protocol one
just increase your skillfulness your
artistry your mastery
of of playing in paradigm space and to
become a
in this new in this post-digital
environment all right protocol 2
bring it right when you're showing up in
an encounter
and i love this with another artist and
by the way that artist might be too
i guarantee you if you enter if you
interact with the two-year-old as if
you're interacting with a
trans-paradigmatic artist
you will have a better encounter and you
will learn more
um she'll she'll have something to teach
you
and the point is to say hey that's
teacherly authority
that happens first and foremost at any
encounter
is your own skillfulness your own
development the thing that happens when
you and i
meet greg what happens is i am
transformed by the encounter
right vice versa right first thing in
the protocol the very first thing is
that i am coming in not just expecting
but intending
and with commitment that it will happen
that i will be transformed in the
account and by the way transformed
for the better and for the better goes
back to protocol one i should say
in terms of my mastery and skillfulness
of navigating reality
and becoming an artist of paradigms in
navigating reality as well
okay so now we get to protocol three all
right now now protocol three
it's in this order right we have to have
to hold it in that fashion protocol
three are kind of like the
heuristics of encounters here's a simple
one
don't kill the other person with
physical violence
it tends to shut things down right it
makes the encounter much less than it
could be
amen but these are heuristics right
that's just uh you know
maybe the game maybe what's happening
right now is you're in combat
maybe it's a beautiful combat maybe what
needs to happen is it you know
i've seen i've seen movies where two
sword fighters encounter each other in a
beautiful dance
which ends up in visit and death but in
the process they both
sought as the as the absolute
fulfillment of their being on the planet
absolutely
all right if that's the nature of what's
up if that's that's what's called for in
the relationship
but as a heuristic that's just a rule of
thumb don't go there
fast you know is that where it needs to
be let it settle well let it show up
that way by the way it'll be sweeter
anyway
you know the the five-fingered man or
the six-fingered man
that was like a whole arc of life right
he looked for him for decades and then
he lost him like you want this you know
if you want to be good it's gonna be
good you can't just like come and
like whack somebody that's good that's
that's an artistry
exactly lacking of artistry it's that
sync
so that's it right you can kind of like
there's the the the protocols
um are so what are some of their
heuristics
there's some simple jurisdiction um yeah
don't ins
don't use your power to insist that you
dictate the game
yeah right yeah yeah you showed up in a
situation where
um no actually there's an even stronger
one
the stronger one which is maybe
somewhere in protocol 2 is something
like
um
[Music]
to the degree to which
your own artistry
supports and calls for nurturing
the other in their capacity so it is
protocol two it's a deeper sense of
protocol two
then do so and so nurturing the other in
the capacity that teacherly moment right
on the one hand you're coming in
expecting to be transformed
on the other hand you're coming in
expecting to transform
but with this nurturing sensibility
right it's not my
it's not my job or my intent to load
code on you i'm not teaching you stuff
i'm not throwing propositions at you
i am supporting you in your own
discovery of your own artist right
right that's a big difference right it
might be like
you seem tired maybe you should get some
rest right you know you're you know
you're not you're not you're not playing
you're it's you know again you're like a
game
yeah yeah it's like a band i'm coming in
and my my uh you know my lead singer is
hungover
well okay i guess there's things that
have to happen now before of course
this thing worked right um and again the
two-year-old's great
it's halftime man nap time is
nap time let's take care of the basics
and you know once i've got that it's
like okay let's think about how
how like many problems it solves if it's
like basic protocol two
is that my i have i take care of the
other
just so they can show up as the
artist that they are totally
right that's that's the base case so so
i'll throw some protocols from my
uh structure on so you know
keep in mind maslow's hierarchy you have
the basics taken care of
right yeah so let's say and obviously
fires are burdened uh
or you don't have oxygen you know you
take care of that stuff
but if the rest of the system if you got
the base two
uh that's physiological safety needs you
get that then look to the other
which is esteem and belonging you know
those are and then if you take care of
that actualization
that's good but you know let's keep
those needs in mind
and can and the other
system that i use the black dot on the
tree uh of
the theory of knowledge tree uh
represents what's called
com mo okay uh that's an integrative
approach to psychological mindfulness
that i
teach folks mo stands for metacognitive
observer
okay so that's we're going to be aware
of our awareness
and be able to stand in that it also
doubles as mo
like your modus operandi so it's like
how do you build that artistry
okay so it's a reminder it's not easy
actually to hold
metacognitive awareness especially if
you're upset you get bumped by life
and then calm obviously is a word but
then it's an acronym
that stands for curiosity acceptance
loving compassion and motivated toward
valued states of being
yeah yeah i like that and i calm as the
return
i went through the words and came back
to calm and the thing that i was coming
up with is like
you know humility and in the context of
humility as something like
if i think about coming off the path
there's there's always
the cilla and the charybdis so one side
is doing
less than the other side is doing more
than
an example i would have is say you know
there's a bunch of people and uh
hold on one moment
um and somebody's having a heart attack
right you know and think about this
terms of almost like
like activist mind somebody do something
okay yes somebody do something this is
another situation
now if you are the only person that
somebody is you
and that something is what you can if
there's a lot of other people
the right thing to do is actually say
somebody do something
and only step in to do something if your
artistry is equal to the event that is
before you
it's not that complicated but but this
this is
you know if i'm if i'm dealing with
let's go back to parenting a very simple
instruction
if i am emotionally overwhelmed
and nutritionally deficient and my
two-year-old is having a tantrum
i'm probably not the best person to be
parenting right now
right it's the best choices to actually
see if there's someone else
who is more whose artistry is equal to
the event that they're encountering
who can actually turn that into a joyful
encounter to use bonuses term
and i think that's crucial right i've
called it in terms of don't
don't bear anybody else's cross right
you've got a thing you're where you're
at you have certain capacities
live those capacities into the world as
fully as you can
but no more and no less right don't blow
your charge if you overtake i think you
were saying that in some ways
yeah yeah many people will tend to try
to carry the whole load and then all of
that flows through them and they just
you know they blow a circuit that's
that's no good right because
we need everybody we need everybody to
just can moving forward
fluidly and smoothly into ever higher
levels of the developmental capacity
right um and so it's one of those
because the marines right slow is smooth
smooth is fast
and that that metaphor is crucial for
gathering that's another good protocol
another good hero yes definitely for
these times in particular
yeah for these times in particular um
so why are we there we're there because
if you if you begin to
sort of back off and say okay well this
is a
this is actually in many ways it's not
that complicated i don't need it i'm not
creating a paradigm
i'm not trying to create a meta paradigm
to to
to position every proposition in its
value
and its sense right i'm actually just
creating
protocols parameters some of which are
more generally applicable some of which
are more contextually relevant
to constrain simplify
really to simplify choices to give rise
to this positive to the highest degree
of possibility
of inter-subjective collaboration in
trans-paradigmatic space
exactly so let's build the protocol
that's on the other side
exactly build a protocol that allows the
framing of the agent
or dual agent dialectic arena right we
got to have some protocols for that
and then let the magic happen in the
arena
yeah yeah okay so then and and and my
point is uh not my point but one of the
things that i keep trying to
kind of bring out there is the amount of
capacity
for change
good change and it's crucial like good
and change both that is unlocked
in this mode is gargantuan
and so back to that notion of like
sometimes you got to build a tool
like right now we're trying to use the
pointy end of a screwdriver
to hammer in a penny nail all right
we're making holes in the wood we're
like bending the nail we're poking
ourselves in the finger
we're way using the wrong tool way way
way
right we're defining a tool right now we
are using transparent mind and the
beginnings of some post
post transfer post paragraph protocols
to be able to support the defining of a
tool
which tool has you know it just kind of
comparatively
has as much capacity to respond to
reality
as the sum total of all of culture
had in relationship to animal behavior
right nicely placed so it's a good idea
it's a good idea to do that it's a very
good choice to do that and
in these times we're just going to
continue to notice
that not doing that is a bad choice
right and and right and let's help
people see
also what is happening so as as the
collapse
of our understanding occurs
okay meaning oh my god what people get
anxious and they regress and what do
they do they cling
to what it is that they feel they know
okay so
many individuals are defaulting to a
clinging of the paradigm
yeah right and exactly the converse that
what the situation calls for
is step outside and look at it don't
like
put all in on it right yeah
or they drop a lower level even even
more right well they just apparently
just progresses into it
well they just go to core belief and you
screwed me and i'm going to attack you
yeah that's that's the foundational kind
of uh but
there you'll see the justification
system collapse into that yeah
um and that's but that's but it will all
be then
as humans will do as persons will then
legitimize
through the paradigm unless they're
really like
you know completely uh emotionally
you know okay cool legitimized through
the paradigm so one of the things that
just came up there
and maybe maybe to the tail end of this
conversation is um
liars specifically sociopaths
right and so here's the here's
it keeps coming up right yeah well these
are they're a problem
they're probably they're a problem
psychopaths even more so dan
schmackenberger kind of helped me get a
psychopath as a sociopath who's capable
of engaging in
high quality long-term strategic
planning okay that's the way he's
defining that term fair enough
flying around all over the place but
that's a there's a real topic
so if i if you know maybe it's protocol
4 or something like that so one of the
challenges
is that if i interact using these
various protocols
and the inter and the encounter i'm
having is actually with the psychopath
i'm in trouble because you know
that's the niche that psychopaths are
are designed to exploit
the charming intelligent ones um and
and that notion of you screwed me so i'm
going to attack you
is the developmental response to the
reality of the emergence of the
possibility if you screwed me
right you know at the end of the day
there the problem is is when the niche
of culture opened up
inside that niche parasitism
of the intersubjective space also opened
up
as a niche and began to explore its
developmental environment
and you know sociopaths and psychopaths
got very
good at exploiting and maintaining and
controlling and
you know implicit everything else so
and i and i've noticed by the way and i
think this is is legit
but but how do i say it's it's it's not
skillful but it's a good operating
heuristic i've noticed that the internet
people
so millennials particularly millennials
like younger millennials
have a strong bias
towards assuming
uh bad guy intra interactive bad guy
and so the person who i'm interacting
with usually somebody i'm interacting
with i'm like seeing online
the idea of grifter right right that the
the
the the the culture the metaculture that
we live in
is so super saturated
with hardcore psychopaths and with
what i call like default or as if
sociopaths i
people who aren't obligate sociopaths
but have adapted to having to be
sociopaths
in this environment that the sort of the
primate is sort of like seeing bad guys
everywhere
because if you don't defend yourself
you're going to be you'll say subject to
parasitism
or pray right so the challenge is okay
we got to get
through that right on the other side of
that we have to find a way to be able to
be quite sensitive to when we're
encountering somebody who is in fact a
psychopath
then we have to have mechanisms for an
autoimmune system as it were we have to
create capsids around that we have to
inhibit that
uh that niche we have to extinguish that
niche right so
the end of the culture story one of the
big pieces of the end of the culture
story is the development of a
highly effective autoimmune system to
that kind of stuff um
and it's an interesting challenge
absolutely a seriously interesting
challenge
absolutely at some other future
conversation we can
uh possibly spend some time riffing off
of
so the justification hypothesis
is the idea that the propositional
language
created the question answer dynamic and
that tipped
okay us from animal mental into culture
and then but that's one idea in uh
the whole justification systems theory
that's one third of it
the second we've been riffing off of
here is the idea that actually then what
that space
is is systems of justification
the best way to think about capital c
culture person plane is really thinking
about that
propositional language system taking off
okay the other
uh part of the triangle is the model of
human consciousness that merges
out of this okay it's called the updated
tripartite model of human consciousness
and that gets into the differentiation
between
our phenomenological consciousness
nonverbal perceptual perspectival
participatory
are private propositional and are public
propositional
okay all right and the dynamic
and it's called updated tripartite
because it's a reference to freud
freud's tripartite is
id ego superego okay so this
updates what freud saw and then tells us
about exactly the kind of dynamics that
are operative
when we have this whole problem of other
deception
which is the justification in the social
world and even self-deception
which is like why would we even actually
deceive ourselves and say actually i'm a
nice guy even when you're brave in like
an a-hole
you believe you're a nice guy that
happens all the time yeah so this
actually provides a framework for the
whole
shadow self where the shadow self comes
with you know what you hide from
yourself
your self consciousness system relative
to your heart and
then how you bs other people and so to
gain
the frequencies across these domains it
provides a way to find the flashlight
so that we can hone in on the ways in
which uh deception
happens and then create systems
protocols that allow clear lines of
communication
that build upon each other in cumulative
and healthy ways
yeah there's a lot there it's it's it is
definitely too much for where we are now
um it feels super ripe though so
we'll do it again i love by the way that
when i when i send you a message say hey
let's talk
you actually come back to me as far as i
can tell faster than the internet could
have worked
um but it's it's thank you you're you're
uh i i stay
you know i live my my system got plugged
into the email world
and i'm like running connections uh all
over it and stand on it so there it is
all right man all right man great
talking to you and jordan glad
i enjoyed it peace